this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
hi everybody this is Anna Hauser with
another episode of software engineering
radio and today I'm interviewing Dave
Thomas of the pragmatic programmers
about software ecology Dave would you
like to start by saying some words but
yourself oh I hate doing that but I'll
I'll try sure I'm Dave Thomas I've been
programming now since Oh a lot program
long enough that you probably need an
archaeologist to find me I started back
in the in the 70s I guess in the last
five six years I've been having a
secondary career as a book publisher
Andy Hunt and myself kind of
accidentally fell into being publishers
we published pragmatic programmer back
in nineteen eight ninety nine and really
liked the experience in that time we're
actually going through another book
publisher addison-wesley so when it came
time to publish a trilogy of books on
basic software practices we thought
would try it ourselves and from there we
kind of just kept doing it so we've now
got something like 60 books in print and
another 50 books under development so
I'm being kept pretty busy on the book
side at the moment but underneath it all
my my passion is still software and I
still write as much code as I can as
often as I can
yeah I can sympathize with that it's
same with me um I came across the term
software I call a team based on on a
workshop you did for in 2001 and well
since I like reading code myself I was
wondering if maybe you could tell our
listeners about how you came up with
this term and what is it about I have to
first say it probably wasn't me that
came up with the term I believe he was
Ward Cunningham but I'm not 100% sure
the workshop was a joint effort of Ward
Cunningham Brian Merrick Andy huntin
myself and it was more an attempt just
to get a discussion going on what we
thought was a much on
appreciated aspect of software
development and after all everybody
spends all the time working out how to
write code so we'll have all the tools
the support the UML diagrams everything
else to help us write code but very
people actually spend any time at all
working out how best to read code and
that's a really big mistake because when
you think about it I would guess that
probably the average software developer
spends maybe 20% of their time writing
code and the rest of time reading it
and yet the training is totally the
other way around so we wanted to start
highlighting the fact that code reading
is as important if not more important to
skill than code writing and what why do
I say that people spend so much time
reading code when you think about it
most the time you're either going back
and looking at existing code or making
changes to it that may be code that you
yourself wrote just five minutes ago but
you're still looking at existing code or
maybe you're called in to fix a bug in
the system and it's 50,000 lines of Java
and you have to find the one line that
has the bug in it or maybe have to add a
new features as an application or
integrate that application with
something else whatever it is you're
sitting there reading code in order to
do your job and as I said we don't think
anybody is taught how to do that
effectively so we would love to try and
find ways of helping people and do them
so how do you go about reading code well
there is no single one way of doing it
to some extent it depends on why you're
trying to do it what what is your
motivation for reading this code there
is a group of people that includes me
who enjoy reading code just because code
is good to read if you can find some
well-written code it's an educational
and it's a fun experience to sit there
and look at it you know how does this
person do this oh that's a really cool
technique I like the way they've done
that you learn stuff about algorithms
you learn stuff about programming you
even learn stuff about how to lay code
out nicely and so that's one reason sort
of recreational code reading if you like
[Laughter]
but you know what I think that's
actually a very important aspect of of
it if you think about any other creative
profession if maybe maybe you're a
writer or a painter you
don't sit there and just write or just
paint if you're a writing student you'll
be reading other people's work in fact
most of your work will be you know going
through and reading the great classics
and reading what other people have done
seeing how other people constructed
books so whatever it is you're writing
if you're a painter
you'll spend time studying other
painters and yet if you're a software
developer you never read anybody else's
code you spend your entire time writing
your own which is an incredibly arrogant
approach to the profession so I think
this idea of recreational code reading
or educational code reading is a vitally
important one and it's much overlooked I
would love to see courses in college a
lot of courses on college which is yeah
which are on code reading and code
appreciation I would like to see a
growing corpus of work which is great
code code that people read them
seriously I don't see why not yeah I
think I've seen something like code gems
or something like that ah sounds sounds
a good approach but most people that I
know most developers that I know um sort
of go like oh no I don't like green code
because it's so difficult there's no way
I can actually get to grips with other
people's code so how could how what's
your advice how should someone go about
approaching code that they don't know
yet well there's a couple of things I
say first of all like anything worth
doing it it repays practice it's not
easy
reading code as you said and that's not
an excuse for not doing it
the second thing is that there are there
are many quick and easy ways of reading
code for example the first thing to
realize is that you don't necessarily
have to understand all of the code that
you're looking at in order to get the
information out that you want and if for
example you're looking at a very
targeted bug fix then the approach to
reading the code will be very different
so if you were for example to be looking
to move the code to a different language
or a different platform or integrate it
into your application in some way so
there are different approaches to take
depending on what you're trying to do
the first thing you have to do when
you're reading code and this is going to
sound very stupid but is to make sure
you've actually got the code I have
wasted so many days so many weeks
probably in my life
tracking down bugs in the wrong version
of a piece of code
or downloading what I thought was you
know the X Y Zed package only to
discover I got the wrong one and it was
just you know and it takes a lot of time
if you're not familiar with the code
pace it takes time for that realization
to come in so the first thing you have
to do is to make sure you have the right
code second thing to do is make sure you
have all of it quite often you'll find
that people are bundling their code up
in weird kind of ways one of the things
you have to be very careful you have is
you have all the code all the libraries
and then all the tests and all the
documentation now if you have tests
you're lucky because the majority of
code does not have tests but you know if
you can find it you want to make sure
you have everything you can get the next
thing you want to do is to put that into
a version control system now the code
may already be in some kind of version
control system depending on that system
you might want to put it into your own
just temporarily
so maybe just copy it across and stick
it into a local git repository or
whatever it might be because you're
gonna be messing with that code and the
last thing you want to do is to make
irreversible changes so sorry so sort of
an interactive approach to reading sort
of reading and modifying the code as a
means to read the code eventually that
will be you will get there but as a very
first step in a way this is kind of like
laying out the ground if you look at
archaeologists you know coming to a site
the first thing they do they won't start
digging what they'll start doing is
preparing the site so they'll put up
some kind of grid that set up reference
marks etc etc this is what we're doing
at this point we're giving ourselves an
environment in which we can have a bit
more control as we're reading the code
and I'm making it sound terribly formal
I mean really it's not a big deal and
just as I could doing a git init in a
repository in its directory
takes like tenth of a second but just
doing that is a really important step
because it means we then have a safety
net in place and we don't have to worry
about messing things up as we go forward
so we have our we have our code in front
of us so then the next question we got
to ask is okay what is it we're trying
to do now maybe what we're trying to do
is to find the cause of a bug and if
you're trying to find a bug then maybe
the bug is an exception gets thrown or
an error messages output in certain
circumstances in those cases your friend
is a source scanning tool something like
grep or something like AK or if you're
in an IDE they typically have you know
search the files in a project for a
particular string and just try and
localize where that problem is coming
from and then from there we can read
backwards after the source code the one
thing I'd say here is there are two
distinct kinds of software archaeology
and by looking at bug fixing I'm kind of
like mixing the two up so what I'd like
to do is step back a bit and first of
all just look at the two different
schools that you have here the first one
is pure reading the first one is just
the ability to scan through the source
and see what's there and the nice thing
about that type of reading is you don't
actually have to
be able to compile or execute the code
the second kind of archaeology is more
complicated because there you do
actually have to create an environment
in which the code runs so if you're
fixing a bug for example you actually
have to be able to reproduce the bug
create a test for it and then fix the
code and that's a whole as a whole extra
level of complication but let's start
just looking at static source analysis
and what you can do about that what I
like to do when I'm looking at a body of
code like that is I will bring the
entire code base up in actions typically
I don't use an IDE typically I'll just
use an editor like textmate on the Mac
but I'll bring all of the code up and I
will shrink the font size down fairly
small and just quickly scan through it
Ward Cunningham in the archeology
workshop I actually talked about a trick
he had where he would load all his
source code into Microsoft Word and then
set the point size down to two points
and what happens is actually it's very
interesting if you do that you lose the
ability to read the code obviously but
what you be able to see is the structure
of the code
and you actually have a whole bunch
revealed by that you can see from the
indentation for example how long things
are you can look for repetitive patterns
you'd be amazed how easy it is to spot
duplicated code if you shrink the code
down and if you scan through that just a
few times back and forth you somehow
build up some kind of subconscious and
map of what's going on and that will
help a lot when it comes to actually
finding stuff later on as I say I don't
use word for that I use text mate but I
take the same kind of approach I'll
shrink the font down and then I'll
scroll very quickly through it I'm gonna
try and read it I'll just scroll and
watch the code go by do you mean did you
do that on a file-by-file basis or did
you concatenate all the files for that
I will do that in the file-by-file basis
typically and I don't necessarily have
to dig into every single file typically
you'll find there'll be kind of
top-level files and then they'll be
library and support files and most
definitely I'll go through the top-level
files I'll also try and find the files
that contain application level logic you
know that the key core logic of the
application and look through that and
again what I'm looking for is the
structuring of the code let's just step
back a bit there's a really interesting
when we use the word software
archaeology we're actually misusing it
greatly because when people talk about
software archaeology they're talking
about the exploration they're talking
about the dig they're talking about
coming back with artifacts but if you
actually read what archeology real you
know you're out in the field archaeology
is it's not really to do with the
artifacts archaeology at Indiana Jones
notwithstanding is that is actually
about understanding of the culture and
the situation in which those artifacts
were used so archaeology is using the
analysis of those artifacts and the
environment in which they were placed in
order to understand the culture that
created them
and one of the things that you can do by
quickly reading through the code is to
start to get a feel for the team that
produced that code
what kind of structure were they using
what kind of methodology were they using
you can probably maybe tell what kind of
IDE they were using were they writing
tests or not were they under some kind
of coding guidelines that restricted the
length of their methods what kind of
modularization philosophy did they have
all these kind of things you can tell
very quickly by just scanning through
the code and I find it really useful to
try and get into the head of the person
who wrote code that I'm trying to read
because then when I have to try and
answer a question I can say you know
what would Fred do and then by answering
that question
I can typically find what I'm looking
for in the code so the code reading is
not really just about code reading
there's a little bit of psychology in
there too
so I will scan through the code quickly
just trying to work out the structure of
it trying to work out there the overall
philosophy of how it worked and then
what I do next really depends on what
I'm trying to accomplish if I'm reading
code for educational purposes then
during my quick scan I will likely have
seen kind of interesting features things
that I want to go back and examine a bit
bit more and then I'll scroll back up or
I'll go back and find those features and
I'll dig in
and along the way I'll be leaving little
breadcrumbs to help me and that's why
it's really nice to stick things into a
source control system because the kind
of breadcrumbs I like to leave are just
comments in the code
and so as I go through it I'll make
notes in the code using a comment so
I'll I'll put a comment marker and then
maybe say my initials and a colon so I
can find it again quickly and just make
those comments to sort of annotate what
I'm discovering
I'll be reading through the code and you
know sort of looking for stuff that's
interesting looking for cool new
techniques cool new features and
annotating them as I go
instead I'm looking for maybe an API so
I can extend this code then obviously
I'll focus in on that section but
typically that section on its own is not
going to be localized I'm going to be
looking at things like Italy and maybe
the parameters have certain types so I
have to go and find out what those types
mean what the constraints are on those
tightly invariants and work backwards
from there if I'm finding a bug then
that's typically not going to be enough
and I'm going to have to go into a
dynamic analysis rather than a static
analysis
one thing I've learned over the years is
that documentation is probably the least
helpful thing Sandhya's ah because it's
a second someone written has written
documentation it's out of date
even if it's something inline like Java
doc it still tends to fall behind in the
heat of battle people update code they
forget to update the comment if it's
separate documentation in some PDF
document or some requirements document
then it's it's going to give you an
overview it's going to give you an idea
of what the thing is supposed to do but
in terms of the details I wouldn't rely
on it at all it's kind of maybe a
cynical view but it's one that's been
borne out by bitter experience so one
thing I am finding very useful is back
only held the workshop which is what
eight years ago testing was something
that was pretty uncommon and it would be
very rare to find a body of code that
actually had unit tests in it nowadays
that's not the case and more and more
teams are using at least unit testing as
a tool to help me get code better
designed and tests unlike documentation
tend not to lie I mean assuming the
tests actually pass then they do tell
you something about the code and so if I
can find unit tests and if I believe
those unit tests are good then I will
spend a fair amount of time looking at
those as well because the unit tests
show me how an API is supposed to be
used the API itself says what it can do
but the unit tests are really reveal
more about the character of the API and
how the developers intended that API to
work and quite often they'll answer
questions that aren't obvious from the
code itself
so if you like the the unit-tests give
you a token or view into the codebase
it's a view that's kind of shifted
through 90 degrees you can attack it
from a different direction so if you can
find tests they're very very valuable
so and when we get on to talking about
the dynamic archeology then we'll have a
whole new use of tests a bit later on
okay so are you saying code is better
off without comments
I'm saying that code is better off
without incorrect comments yes
and I'm saying that the majority of
comments are obsolete in code so that
code yes is better off without comments
in general I think that the most
successful commenting scheme for code is
a sparse one I think people who write
little novels at the top of each one of
their methods are unlikely to come back
and correct them I think they're
spending too much time duplicating
information I mean why write a comment
that says add one to the number of
transactions and then write transactions
equals transactions plus one it just
doesn't make any sense so I think you
know it may feel good at the time there
may be some kind of big virtuous shine
that you get because you wrote
documentation and everybody knows that
writing documentation although painful
and boring is good for you it doesn't
really help that much yes I think the
main reason for that is organizational
culture organizational guidelines that
kind of thing because otherwise I don't
think it would happen as much I think
there's a lot of that I think there are
also a lot of developers who frankly are
nervous about writing code
I think code is the thing that reveals
whether or not something has been done
correctly whether something works and if
you can put off the evil moment then
it's a good thing and there's nothing
better to put up the good moment than
you know writing three or four pages of
comments so I think that happens as well
but what for whatever the reason I think
that if I see code that has a lot of
comments then I tend to ignore them
simply because I don't find them very
useful what I appreciate as a code
reader is reading about the why you know
I'm not that interested in the how
because the code shows me the how and
I'm not interested particularly in you
know a list of parameter names and types
in the comments because that's what the
code shows me but what I really am
interested in is why did they do it this
way not that way
you know and those are the kind of
decisions that help you get inside the
head of the people writing the code so
if you are writing comments you know
don't duplicate what's in the code
that's totally pointless and it will
guarantee to get out of date as you
change the code did you forget the
higher level stuff the abstract things
say you know why we took this approach
why this parameter is done this way not
that way you know and keep it up at that
level the other thing that's really
useful when I'm reading comments is
navigational comments particularly if
for example you know this algorithm
comes off you know this book or this
website or go sees this external
configuration file to see how this works
or whatever it might be things that help
me find my way around are incredibly
useful yeah it makes sense um you you
may mention something well some time ago
that you sometimes like to go for for
the core files core code the the
application scope logic how do you find
that I mean let's say you download a
huge project or have a huge project of
couple hundred thousand lines how do you
actually find the key parts good good
question and again it depends on the
program and the programmer sometimes so
you sort of start skimming the code to
get an understanding of the culture I'll
get into the head of the program and
that helps you as a first step well
there there are a couple of things you
can look for first of all you can
normally find the helper files that the
libraries by looking for self-contained
classes self-contained
modules that you know you just do there
are it's basically just a class that
sits on a file
they are obviously instantiated
somewhere else and they're controlled
from somewhere else so those are clearly
not the top level the top level is going
to be the thing that does the
instantiating it's gonna be them goes
and finds the main business objects
loads them up and does whatever it has
to do well in treating times of
dependency injection it's not quite as
simple as that is it that is true that
is very true and actually that's one of
the reasons I in general I'm not very
happy with the DI style of development
because I think it actually seals the
code quite a lot when it comes to
and a lot of people say oh it decouples
etc etc but what it really does is it
gives you another dimension that you
actually have to read an or to be able
to understand the code so that's you
know maybe a contrary opinion there but
it's it's it's kind of true one of the
things I look for to find the main file
again it depends on a programmer is
quite often there'll be a directory
structure or a module structure that
makes it obvious so the main files will
be at somewhere at a top level quite
often just because people are lazy the
main file will be the biggest one it
kind of sad to say but it's just happens
to be the way it falls out so if you can
find one big honking file quite often
that contains like a four hundred line
method then you know that's probably the
controlling thing that you're looking
for and obviously you can trace it
through by looking at the at the you
know the entry point the main or
whatever it might be
and following it through there the other
trick that I like to use is I will find
the name of I'll think of a name that I
think represents a key concept in the
code and then I'll grep the source files
for it and I'll just basically do a grep
- and to try and find who who actually
has the most occurrences of those names
and by doing sort of like like you can
your domain knowledge to get a grip on
this structure yeah and it may not even
be the main knowledge I mean if I'm
dealing with another things example an
application of just shipping then it
could well be I'll just search for
postage or ship or package or something
like that I mean I mean maybe that is
domain knowledge I guess but it's kind
of common sense as well but simply
looking for the high level concepts it
will typically lead you into that that
main area
and then once you're there it's
religious question of again focusing
what why are you there what are you
doing there
and then you know following the various
tendrils out it's just in passing I
would say that if you are doing serious
code archeology you owe it to yourself
to learn the command line because you
cannot do it as effectively inside an
IDE you can do a lot of stuff in an ID
and certainly IDE is of great for doing
things like reverse engineering UML
diagrams of that happens to be your bent
but to do decent searching and powerful
searching you really do need to learn
the command line you know you need to
learn tools like grep or AK and you need
to learn pipelines because if you have a
lot of source code then grep is going to
return a lot of values and you're going
to want to be able to filter those
results so you want to be able to use
grep pipe the output through maybe
another grip or a word count or
something else it's just be able to get
a sense of what's going on in a very
very common pattern for me this is I'll
gret for something and see that I get
maybe 500 lines come out but most of
those lines will contain stuff that I
know is not relevant to what I'm looking
for so I'll do I'll pipe the output
through another grep either looking for
some specific positive string or quite
often using grep minus V which means
ignore lines that match this pattern so
I'll say find every line that contains
this but not this and that's a very
powerful technique to be able to isolate
things very quickly in a bunch of source
code and as far as I know that's a
pretty difficult thing to do in IDE s so
as I say I recommend getting comfortable
with with user tools what degree would
you say that
architectural patterns are helpful for
for getting an understanding of the
overall structure of applications in
practice oh dear you've just pushed a
hot button I think that
if you have a team that has got the
pattern religion then clearly that is a
useful technique to be able to
understand the decisions they've made
when their structure in their code Andy
and I always used to joke that you could
always spot a team that had bought a
copy of design patterns because they
couldn't write hello world without three
decorators a visitor and I mean serious
I mean it's like you know I have to use
a pattern every single class I write I
have to be able to say in the comment
box implements the xxx and it just went
totally off and a lot of people
misunderstood what patterns were
everybody thought patterns were kind of
like software Lego and you know I'll
construct my software by building it out
of a whole group of patterns and that
totally misses the point patterns are
not a construction device patterns are a
a way of dealing with common issues when
you're writing code
there are idioms they're not designs but
if you have people forget that and so
we'll end up with code like that if
that's the case if you're seeing code
where class names have the names of
patterns embedded in them and that's
clearly a hint that the following
structure Abbes something close to the
pattern however again my experience has
been that many teams will use the name
of pattern but not really understand
what they're doing and so although you
may find a class called you know a stock
visitor it may well not be anything
close to a true visitor pattern so you
know you have to treat that very very
carefully if you if you see that in code
I see what you mean but I was thinking
at the at the larger level like
understanding layers and the
understanding the team head of layers in
large application or let's say you you
have some kind of well
model-view-controller
based system we
several levels of models whatever um do
you find that these kind of structures
are helpful to have the back your mind
or is what you just said Valadez or true
as well at the larger level I think it's
definitely helpful to have in your mind
because it gives you hints as to where
things may be but again I think the the
devil is in the details and so if you
get it into your head that this is a
good MVC design and therefore there is
no business logic in the view I think
you'll be sadly disappointed with you
know 90% of the MVC implementations out
there you know and so if you're sitting
there and you have this preconceived
idea that this is some kind of you know
ideal one MVC and then you're looking
for you know some particular piece of
logic or looking for a validation or
whatever it might be you can fool
yourself into not finding it so I try to
keep an open mind now having said that
that's one of the reasons that the
initial quick read-through really helps
because you know I'm being a bit cynical
here there are teams that do it right or
there are teams that obviously get some
of it and you can understand what parts
they've done so if you read through and
discover hey they know what they're
doing and there is no business logic in
the video or whatever it might be then
that does help and you can you can work
from there so I think pageants are a
hint that they give you something to to
look at as you're reading through and
then you can make your own mind off this
- whether in Act in fact there actually
have been a bade and whether they're
useful or they're not
um and you're right there's also a large
larger structuring pattern that you have
to understand you know how does the
whole program hang together it's
actually surprising how much you can
read without actually understanding that
it's it's possible to actually get a
whole bunch out of a program without
understanding it's it's sort of macro
structure but obviously if you don't do
any work on it then you have to
understand that as well and if you're
lucky the breakdown of the source will
help you do that they'll modularize such
a stuff in such a way that you can work
that one out
and then again maybe the naming will
help you there but sometimes you just
have to fall back on executing it and
seeing what happens which gets us or it
sounds like it gets us to the dynamic
archeology what you're talking about
right right because everything we've
done so far has been pure passive
reading as the source yeah we'd be maybe
adding annotations as we go through but
we haven't been trying to execute that
source so the next thing that we'd want
you to do is to turn run it and this is
where life gets interesting depending on
where the source comes from because very
few pieces of source exist in isolation
they need an environment in which they
can run they'll need libraries they'll
need utilities they'll need a certain
database configuration actually the
connection to that database they'll need
to be put into some kind of container
possibly whatever it might be and so you
relying very heavily on the people who
wrote that code giving you these strong
hints at the minimum of how to put it
all together and how to run it in the
ideal world you'll have some kind of
executable script whether it's a make
file or ant task or maven or rake or
whatever it might be you'll have
something that actually helps the
application dish itself together and
start running
if you're doing archeology on those and
source projects for example then if it's
a C style project you'll probably find a
configured or in script which means that
they've been considerate enough to use
Auto Kampf you'll find a make file to
build it and that will give you some
very strong hints but you will probably
find yourself in dependency hell you
know for the first day or two as you try
and get this thing just to compile and
then finally to load that is itself is
not necessarily a bad thing
because it also gives you an idea of
what this program is doing you know if
you suddenly find it using XSLT library
then you'll know it's doing so I'll see
somewhere probably and that's actually
kind of important information to gather
the other thing that's the most
frustrating is this stage is that
particularly this is older code and by
old I here mean maybe two plus years but
it's seriously the way the world is
changing
they may well rely on old versions of
libraries that they haven't documented a
particularly are using so you'll see
they use some you know they never have a
requirement for whatever it might be so
you download the latest version of it
and the thing just doesn't work or
there's missing entry points or whatever
it might be and so you find yourself
then going back and trying to guess
versions of libraries that work with
this particular software so there's a
lot of detective work that takes place
in this in this section and it's very
frustrating defective work though the
very worst I mean the days where you
just want to throw your computer through
the window are the days where you say oh
look it needs this library so you
download that library and that library
itself has fifteen other dependencies
and you download those and you get the
whole thing to compile and then discover
you using the wrong version of it and
you have to throw it all the way and
start again in those environments if you
find yourself in a serious environment
like that one thing that I've tried
doing has been fairly successful for me
is I'll actually set up a virtual
machine I will run inside a sandboxed
machine so I'll use something like
VirtualBox
and load up an operating system inside
my own offering system and that means
that I can download libraries and then
if I get it wrong I just blow the whole
thing away and start again this applies
particularly this isn't so much for Java
but for the C style libraries that NIT
themselves in globally into your system
you know they'll load themselves in to
use a local however it might be those
things are a real pain to get rid of and
being able to just blow the whole thing
away and start again actually saves a
lot of time the other hint I've got when
you're in that stage is if the people
who wrote the software did not provide a
script to set up everything you need now
is your time to do it because as you go
forward you will find yourself having to
rerun those installations if you get
something wrong you may have to blow it
off and start again and having a script
that does what you want to do will save
you a whole bunch of time and the next
person that comes along to look at this
code will will build a statue to you
because you've made their life so much
easier yeah so it makes your life easier
it makes their life easier and that
script could be nothing more than you
know issuing some curl commands to
download software and then whatever the
build instruction is for software just
not to be elegant doesn't it be neat it
just has to get something done so that's
you know step one to get the thing
running step well then you've got
yourself an executable your should just
do something with it and that also is
often a challenge because maybe the data
the application needs a database and so
you'll have to find some way of working
at what the schema is creating that
database and then working out how to
connect the application to that database
maybe some web application it needs to
go to some container somehow again
hopefully they'll have automated that
but you just have to make sure so at
some point in the process you've
actually got yourself a running
application so then the next thing is
what do you do with it is this actually
is where the documentation can come in
useful because documentation at that
kind of level it may be the user level
will give you a better idea of how the
software is supposed to work it probably
won't be exactly accurate but it will at
least tell you that you know if you want
to do this kind of thing then this is
the menu you want to be going to or this
is the button you want to be pushing
whatever it might be so you know yeah
you could use documentation at that
level so once you've got yourself a
running program this is where the fun
starts
because now you can start doing dynamic
archaeology and there are a whole host
of ways of doing that some people like
to bring the application up in their IDs
or whatever they might use and use the
debugger to set breakpoints to single
step through it to watch the flow of
execution I think that's really useful
but it's also quite hard to get right
setting breakpoints is one of those
things where if you get it right it's
great if you get it wrong it's
incredibly frustration because you set
the breakpoint and then you know you go
through the whole setup manually and get
the thing to work it and suddenly the
breakpoint doesn't fire because it's
going through the else branch not the if
branch or whatever else so that can be
really kind of tricky so I tend not to
use breakpoints as much as I will insert
code that will raise an exception so if
I if I want to see what's going on
I will stick you know whatever the you
throw or raise or whatever the statement
is in a particular language in at a
particular point and that gives me two
things first of all it means that
whenever I go through there it's going
to blow up and that means I get to see
something happening and I get a stack
trace and if I'm lucky I get a stack
trace it also shows me the values of
parameters and everything else so I can
see where I came from and quite often
that information is really important the
other nice thing about those is you can
just leave them in the code and then
they will blow up you know at some point
in the future as well so if there was
some case that you weren't you sure
about you know why is it that you know
they had this code in here in the first
place
stick a fail in and then just you know
over the course of playing with the code
at some point that exception may get
triggered and if it does then you be
able to seize the state and why it got
there so that's kind of useful I know a
lot of people use kind of print Lindy
bugging they'll stick you know Protess
or print Lenore whatever the equivalent
is in your language into the code that
can be useful but it can also get very
verbose very quickly so I think that's
going to be used very locally just to
look at particular problems in general I
find that less useful than raising
exceptions things that are also very
useful our execution profilers because
not only can you find out the the
coverage of the codes and see where the
code is being used but you can also see
where the codes not being used and again
that can be interesting and pertinent
information when you're trying to work
out how to change this program and last
but by no means least in fact last but
probably first remember we're talking
about tests earlier on if you are in a
situation where your your programmers
does actually come with tests then you
should probably first go out and
sacrifice some small animals just in
gratitude but you should then go and try
and run them and see if they actually
execute them and maybe one time in a
hundred they will well I mean as you
know code rots
if you leave if you leave code
unattended for too long you know it's
fall off it in things and it just stops
working and one of the things that
reveals that is tests I don't know why
but you know you can get some code and
apparently the all the tests must have
passed at some point because they
shipped it and then two years later when
you try and run it for some reason you
get 17 failures it's just one of those
things but even so the tests if you can
get the tests to the point where they
even try and run then you're in a really
good position because you can then dig
in and actually play with the code from
the test point of view if you don't have
to
then here is a strong suggestion think
about adding them now I'm not saying
here that you you you look at your
hundred thousand lines of code and say
oh I know what I'll do today I'm gonna
write 150 thousand lines of tests yes
that's obviously not not where you go
but if you are investigating an area and
here I'm not just talking about bug
fixes I'm also talking about the
educational kind of testing if you are
investigating an area then you'll your
form hypotheses in your head you know
okay I believe this method those this or
I believe this parameter means that well
there is no better way of testing that
hypothesis than writing a test so write
an exploratory test that just test that
one hypothesis and if you're lucky and
if the code is we are halfway decently
written you'll be able to sq that test
and say oh yeah I was right or oh no
that was not what it did in the first
place and if you leave those tests lying
around then the next person to come to
your Creek that code will have a
slightly me on better position than you
had when it comes to understanding it so
I'd love writing little exploratory
tests now sometimes those tests just
aren't possible because sometimes the
efforts of setting up the environment in
order to be able to run this one piece
of code it's just too much and in those
cases are fall back on you know putting
exception in the in the method and
looking the parameters and this kind of
thing but if I can get away with writing
tests I love that as a technique for
both understanding and also documenting
what a chunk of code does
what would you say is a particularly
well readable programming language
and there's all kinds of obfuscated
whatever contests so the opposite of
that what language makes reading
particularly easy in your experience I
think that every language is
it's potentially readable I think the
first thing is that to some extent of
fluency and readability are in the
reader as much as the writer in order to
be able to understand the language you
actually have to know that language in
the same way you do with a human
language you know I mean I you know I
that there may be the world's you know
prettiest piece of serbo-croatian poetry
that wouldn't make you know wouldn't be
in any way appealing to me because I
don't understand it and the same with
code people who say oh pearl is ugly are
people that have listed it superficially
and haven't actually taken the time to
learn pearl I mean there are things that
do make pearl hard to read but it's it's
a language and you have to learn what
all the various symbols mean what all
the various conventions mean what was
various idioms mean before you can hope
to make that judgment that pearl is ugly
or coal is nice there are some very
elegant pieces of coal pearl code and
there are some very ugly pieces of
chrome pearl code there's some very
elegant pieces of Java there are elegant
pieces of COBOL it's it's really I think
elegance is language agnostic I think a
lot of people get very religious about
languages and say oh this language is a
lot easier to reason this it's not it's
just you have to learn the language you
have to understand the language before a
language makes sense I think this sort
of goes back to what you said about
getting into the head of people to not
only know the language but also to try
to understand their particular style
their particular culture of using the
language their idioms absolutely it Edea
ms is a really good word and that's a
really key word because people will use
idioms and the more you expose yourself
to those idioms the better the program
you'll be because if you keep those in
your back of your head then the next
time you have that kind of problem to
solve you'll be able to use our idiom so
yeah I strongly believe that getting
into the head of the people and
understanding there's a style in which
their writing is crucially important
so let's say some of our listeners find
this idea fascinating one who get
started with reading foreign code what
would be your practical advice for the
people who have not done a lot of code
we need to get started
sort of
creet level okay they do excellent
questions excellent question
I think the the first thing is not to be
too ambitious you are doing something
which is very very worthwhile but you're
also doing something which is actually
quite difficult so don't you know set
yourself the job of understanding the
Linux kernel as your first coding
exercise I think first of all stick to a
language you know well so if you're a
Java programmer then say okay I will
lead ins learn some Java code if I'm a
c-sharp I'll do C shop then choose I
would suggest just choose an open-source
project that has some vague interest to
you and download the source aim for
something which is maybe five to twenty
thousand lines of code something in that
kind of area and then knowing that piece
of software give yourself just a couple
of simple questions to ask and let's try
think an example a say for example
you're a Java programmer then maybe you
download a library that creates PDFs say
simplify text and so you've got this
lump of code in front of you know trying
to understand how it works
so ask yourself okay can it produce
compressed PDFs and if so what mechanism
does it use now that's actually a
relatively simple question to answer in
kind of code
archaeology centers because you're going
to be looking for a couple of potential
key phrases in the source that will help
you I mean a simple grep for compress
may well just answer the question or you
can choose you know you know some other
keywords that would help you find what
compressions is using or ask yourself
okay aids does it support Unicode and if
so how and look for those kind of
answers that's because they're practical
problems that you may well bump into you
know if if I download this package and I
want to know what is my support for
Unicode well I could go read the
documentation or he just look at the
source and say okay what does it do with
characters that aren't built into the
printer
you know how does it handle up this kind
of thing so download some source code
and answer some very basic questions the
next time you bump into something
surprising when you're using some
external software don't just shrug it
off but save yourself the challenge of
finding out why and we go and download
the source code and actually work out
what's going on and you may say that's a
big big waste of time it's not its study
that will repay itself Chad Fowler and I
do a studio on advanced Ruby and the
second topic we cover on the first day
is reading the source code of the Ruby
interpreter
oh we do that because I mean Ruby
obviously is a high level language it's
got its own syntax and everything else
but underneath it all it's written in a
mixture of Ruby and C and the the guts
of it the the the core of the Ruby
interpreter at least Matz's Ruby
interpreter is odd and older is maybe
ten fifteen thousand lines of C code and
that is C code that is very well
structured very well put together I mean
the naming is a bit weird
but it's got a very consistent structure
and it repays study it's because it's
answers questions that are not
documented anywhere so you can go into
the source code and find out now is
there a difference between this method
or that method or if I got this weird
exception what does it mean and so we
show students how they understand or how
to understand the both the lexical side
of Ruby and also the interpreter side of
Ruby in the source code and it people go
wow you know I never knew all that
information which is sitting there and
it's there for the taking
so that's an interesting thing to try
and do I mean if you're a Python
programmer let's do the same thing and
just dig around and see how it works
because you kind of owe it to yourself
and in the pragmatic programmer we have
a section on beware of evil wizards
there's a whole booth for people well no
I mean you think about it there's a lot
of people who use IDE s and the IDS have
some kind of code generation built in
and it may well be that you can click a
button to create a project and I means
last time we looked and this was a long
time ago the last time we looked if
you're using I think it was a visual
studio to create an empty project
it creates over a thousand lines of
source code
I bet you probably at least 50% of the
people that do that have no idea what
that thousand lines of source code do
and so they're sitting there developing
their applications on a foundation that
they themselves don't understand and if
something went wrong or something
unexpected happens they're totally at a
loss because they have no knowledge of
how their own application works mm-hmm
it happened to me today
um III did a code review with a
colleague and asked him why he did
things in this particular way and he
said well the IDE did that for me right
the second reason for him yeah
absolutely right and if that happens to
blow up you know and if that happens to
blow up in production and you're faced
with that you know you're lost
absolutely lost so that's a that's
another form of coding archaeology that
I would strongly recommend that people
do is to get into you know the
environment they're using and so if
you're a Perl or Python or a PHP or Ruby
programmer understand the interpreter
and understand why because I'm not
saying you have to be you know be able
to write anything you don't have to be
you turn yourself into a C programmer or
an assembler programmer but whatever it
might be but at least understand the
structure I mean you can understand the
see if you can write any block
structured language you can understand C
and that's all you need to be able to do
you just need to read through it and you
know see what's going on it will really
really help so again that's kind of like
maybe part two of the the road to code
reading Nirvana is is to understand your
environments and use code reading to
understand what's going on in the
applications your writing and then
really part three I guess is as you
start to get proficient at it you'll
find yourself be able to take on things
that you previously wouldn't be able to
do and that will be larger and larger
bodies of code if you do that you might
want to think about kind of remembering
them somewhere and that's where it's
nice to have a version control
repository we talked about having a
repository lying around locally so if
you modify the code
you can see what modifications you've
made and keep track of them well it's
also useful to have that repository
because if you find little gems
they'll be in your repository still I
mean I keep a little repository down on
my machine here it used to be
subversion now it's get all stuff I
found and it you know it's not runnable
code it's just little chunks of code
like a little scrapbook of useful little
stuff uses little algorithms and you
know it maybe even just like that's a
really cool way of laying out that piece
of code and I'll just keep it lying
around and maybe once every six months
or so I'll just open the whole thing up
I just quickly read through to remind
myself what's in there and again that's
kind of like you know in the same way
that people will go through great works
of literature and you know highlight
sections that are significant you know
they'll write essays on you know just
the single sentences and what they mean
it's the same kind of thing we're doing
analysis and we're doing and now
criticism on the content of the supper
reading yeah that's really important
yeah thank you very much for for all
these insights into reading source code
um the time is almost up is there any
last words anything else you would like
to share with our listeners well one
thing that
I live in in in Texas here as you can
probably tell from my accent and there
are a lot of people get together here
and do book clubs where they'll sit down
and now you don't meet up at a coffee
shop or somewhere and they'll assign
themselves a book and then every week
they'll get together and discuss the
next chapter or two chapters that ever
might be and you know what was the
author intent of above at the same time
we have a lot of groups to get together
and there'll be like a Java users group
and there'll be a Ruby user group they
get together and you know in she's
basically complaining about the state of
the job market but you know in theory
they'll be talking about you know their
programming language what you might want
to consider doing is combining the two
ideas and having a group that gets
together and talks about some code so
you could assign yourself code and the
group could look at it and maybe give a
specific task so you'll say you know I
want you to look at this this module or
these modules or yeah analyze how this
works whatever it might be and then get
together and talk about what you can't
what you what you discover it sounds
kind of a little bit geeky it sounds a
little bit weird but I think you'd be
surprised at the kind of insights that
different people have reading the same
code it's very easy to get locked into a
particular way of thinking if you allow
other people's ideas to come in
then suddenly code becomes a whole lot
richer the other thing that you can do
when you when you get together as a
group is you can kind of hone your
critical ideas because I don't think you
necessarily want to look at just great
works of code I mean if nothing else
they're kind of hard to find but look at
any piece of code and say I like this I
love the way he did this I love this
treachery that she used over here but
this was horrible and you know did you
notice that this did this this and this
when they could have done it this way
instead and everything else and those
are the kind of discussions that in my
experience are the most interesting
because you know you sit there and you
say well clearly this is a bad idea and
then someone says well actually no it
was good because of this and then the
whole group gets going too
about that particular decision it's
actually a deep way of learning about
coding so I guess I'm gonna leave you
with anything it's two things one is
code reading is probably as important if
not more important than code writing and
secondly doing it in a group is a lot
more fun than doing it on your own yes
well thank you very much for taking the
time to share all these things
absolutely my pleasure and thanks
everybody for listening to radio thanks
for listening to software engineering
radio software engineer radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
se - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
via the website or you can advertise for
su radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious links and the
slash dot button to contact the team
please send email to team @ s e - radio
net or if you specific to an episode
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can react to
your comments this episode of se radio
as well as all other episodes are
licensed under the creative comments 2.5
license please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the pot site Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas Achtung